Finding Aid for Michael A. Gorman Papers, 1920-1958
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael A. Gorman papers 1920-1958
Gorman, Michael (Michael Arthur), 1892-1958.
85238 Aa 2
Editor of the Flint Journal. Correspondence and topical files concerning his newspaper career in Flint, the role of the Flint Journal in the development of the city, the General Motors sit-down strike of 1937, and the position of automobile industry to Flint; and photographs.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Flint Journal through editorial librarian William D. Chase (donor no. 3907 ) and came to the library in 1977.
The collection is open to research.
Michael Gorman was born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1892. He began his journalism career in 1910 as a sports and general reporter for the Saginaw Courier-Herald. This association was rather brief and in 1913, Gorman became the telegram editor of the Saginaw News. During what was to become a fifteen year association with the Saginaw newspaper, Gorman rose to become city editor and finally managing editor from 1916 until 1928 when he moved to Flint.
As editor of the Flint Journal from 1928 until his death in October 1958, Gorman was witness to the development of Flint as an important center for the automobile industry. He reported on the influence of General Motors in the city's affairs, the turmoil arising out of the sit-down strike of 1937, and the city's burgeoning cultural and civic programs, i.e., the Flint Redevelopment Project, the Flint Institute of Arts, and the Flint campus of the University of Michigan.
The Gorman papers reflect the relationship between a local newspaper and the community it served. The collection comprises two linear feet of correspondence and topical files from the period 1928 to 1958. Representing but a selection of Gorman's original files, this remnant appears to include correspondence which Gorman considered to be most important. The correspondence includes substantive material as well as letters of autograph value only.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Flint.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Communism.; Depressions--1929--Michigan--Flint.; Flint (Mich.); Flint (Mich.)--History.; Flint journal.; General Motors Corporation.; Gorman, Michael A. (Michael Arthur), 1892-1958.; Jews--Michigan.; Journalists--Michigan--Flint.; Michigan. Civil Service Study Commission.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; American newspapers--Michigan--Flint.; Presidents--United States--Election--1956.; Sit-down strikes--Michigan--Flint.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; China--History--1949-1976.; General Motors Corporation Sit-Down Strike, 1936-1937.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Celebrations.; Costumes.; Flint (Mich.); General Motors Corporation.; Gorman, Michael A. (Michael Arthur), 1892-1958.; Saginaw High School (Saginaw, Mich.)
Contributors:
Allen, Fred, 1894-1956.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Curtice, Harlow Herbert, 1893-1962.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Gerber, Daniel F., 1898-1974.; Godfrey, Arthur, 1903-1983.; Harmon, Tom, 1919-1990.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968.; Knudsen, William S., 1879-1948.; Landers, Ann.; Montgomery, George, 1916-2000; Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Pound, Arthur, 1884-1966.; Rockwell, Norman, 1894-1978.; Shore, Dinah, 1917-1994.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Sloan, Alfred P. (Alfred Pritchard), 1875-1966.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Other Papers
  - Undated 1920-1958, 16 folders (Box 1)
- Topical files circa 1928-1958
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Daily News 1934 (Box 1)
  - Atwood, Edwin W. 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Bridgeman, Luther H. 1953 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Russell S. 1943-1947 (Box 1)
  - Chase, William D. 1948-1953 (Box 1)
  - Chakravorti, Robi 1954 (Box 1)
  - Childs, Richard B. 1941-1953 (Box 1)
  - Coates, Harris 1943-1950 (Box 1)
  - Conway, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - Cook, Joyce 1940-1954 (Box 1)
  - Cossman, Mauri (Box 1)
  - Cranbrook Institute of Science 1933, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Curry, Ralph 1936-1958 (Box 1)
  - Curtice, Harlow H. 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Diehm, Harold 1949 (Box 1)
  - Dowly, Homer 1948-1954 (Box 1)
  - "Early Bird"/organization of pioneer aviators 1935-1936, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Flint
    - "Bank Scandal" 1929 (Box 1)
    - Banking and Flint's Economic Rehabilitation 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - Centennial 1955 (Box 1)
    - Community organizations
      - Boy Scouts 1948, 1955, 1957 (Box 1)
      - The Clara Elizabeth Fund for maternal health 1935 (Box 1)
      - The Clara Elizabeth Fund for maternal health Budget 1955 (Box 1)
      - Community Fund, Inc. 1934-1937, 1940-1947 (Box 1)
      - Community Music Association 1936-1941, 1954 (Box 1)
      - Community Players 1941 (Box 1)
      - Four-H-Club 1955 (Box 1)
      - Girl Scouts 1955 (Box 1)
      - Goodwill Industry 1957 (Box 1)
      - Kiwanis International 1922, 1955 (Box 1)
      - Lion's Club 1936 (Box 1)
      - C.S. Mott Foundation 1938-1957 (Box 1)
      - N.A.A.C.P. 1941 (Box 1)
      - Red Cross 1942, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
      - Relief Commission 1931-1934 (Box 1)
      - Reserve Armory 1955-1957 (Box 1)
      - Town Hall 1940 (Box 1)
      - Salvation Army 1940 (Box 1)
      - Y.M.C.A. 1940 (Box 1)
    - Flint College and Cultural Development 1954-1957, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Flint History (Box 2)
  - Flint Institute of Arts, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Flint Journal
    - Correspondence
      - 1928, 1933-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 2)
    - Agency reports 1944-1947, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Editors Meeting 1935, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Printed materials (Box 2)
    - Voting Survey 1940 (Box 2)
    - Sponsorship of Community projects
      - Soap Box Derby 1936 (Box 2)
      - Sports and Golden Gloves 1934-1937, 1940-1941, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Special editions (Box 2)
    - Weather Bureau 1934 (Box 2)
    - Job applications 1934-1936 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Flint Public Library 1936-1937, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Flint River Redevelopment Project 1954, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Gapper, Gordon S. 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - General Motors
    - Correspondence 1930-1955 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Alfred Sloan, Jr., 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - General Motors "Sit Down Strike"
    - Correspondence 1932-1937 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1937, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Newspapers 1937 (Box 2)
    - Articles 1937 (Box 2)
    - Printed materials (Box 2)
    - Flint Alliance 1937 (Box 2)
    - Mechanics Educational Society of America 1937 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Gampetroni, Lou 1954 (Box 2)
  - Gover, Raymond 1955 (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Press 1932, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Gundry, Ray 1954 (Box 2)
  - Hamady, Michael and Robert 1954 (Box 2)
  - Hart, Adam Thomas 1933-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Herrick, Robert C. 1940-1951 (Box 2)
  - Jackson City Patriot 1934-1936 (Box 2)
  - Jenkins, Guy 1957 (Box 2)
  - Kalamazoo Gazette 1935 (Box 2)
  - Knisley, Bertha 1955 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Roland 1939, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Muskegon Chronicle 1934 (Box 2)
  - Noble, William 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Oslon, Marjorie 1951, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Petrill, Jack 1949, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Pound, Arthur (Box 2)
  - Summary of Nominations for Pulitzer Prize in Journalism 1950 (Box 2)
  - Richard, Steve 1950 (Box 2)
  - Roth, Steve 1942 (Box 2)
  - St. Joseph Hospital, Nazareth 1952 (Box 2)
  - Sanderson, Eldon 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Saginaw News (Box 2)
  - Scott, Roland 1954 (Box 2)
  - Scott, Walter 1941 (Box 2)
  - Short, Perry (Box 2)
  - Summerfield, Arthur (Box 2)
  - Tomasi, Dominic 1948 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan (Box 2)
  - University Press Club (Box 2)
  - Weil, Louis 1934 (Box 2)
  - Wilhelm, Allan 1954 (Box 2)
  - Yacomb, George 1955 (Box 2)
- Personal
  - Christmas Cards (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Allen, Fred, 1894-1956.
Jan. 17, 1952
Cobo, Albert Eugene, 1893-1957.
Dec. 2, 1955
Curtice, Harlow Herbert, 1893-1962.
Oct. 24, 1929; Oct. 28, 1953; Nov. 12, 1953; Dec. 28, 1953; and topical file folder
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edward), 1902-1971.
Dec. 20, 1948; Nov. 10, 1950; Mar. 20, 1952; Apr. 12, 1952; July 12, 1952; July 29, 1952; Nov. 10, 1952; July 3, 1953; Nov. 19, 1953; Nov. 23, 1953; Dec. 17, 1954
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.
Apr.28, 1953; May 19, 1953; Mar. 15, 1954; Aug. 25, 1954; Sept. 7, 1955; Nov. 9, 1956; Mar. 24, 1958
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Sept. 30, 1936
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-
June 13, 1953; June 18, 1953; Apr. 21, 1955
Gerber, Daniel F 1898-1974.
Apr. 29, 1955
Godfrey, Arthur, 1903-1983.
Mar. 23, 1953; Apr. 3, 1953
Harmon, Tom, 1919-1990.
Nov. 13, 1946; Nov. 7, 1947; Dec. 12, 1950; Dec. 21, 1950; Dec. 5, 1955
Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-
Apr. 10, 1952; June 7, 1952; June 3, 1955
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.
Nov. 26, 1948; Apr. 29, 1950; July 6, 1955
Keller, Helen Adams, 1880-1968.
Dec. 18, 1940
Knudsen, William S., 1879-1948.
Nov. 8, 1934; June 18, 1945
Landers, Ann
Apr. 13, 1957; June 17, 1957; June 21, 1957; June 25, 1957
Montgomery, George, 1916-
Sept. 9, 1955; Sept. 15, 1955; Sept. 22, 1955
Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.
Sept. 8, 1920; Mar. 3, 1942; Oct. 2, 1954
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-
Aug. 26, 1953; Sept. 29, 1953; Apr. 28, 1954; July 10, 1954; July 22, 1954; Apr. 1, 1955; Apr. 7, 1955; Sept. 2, 1955; Sept. 9, 1955; Oct. 6, 1955; Nov. 2, 1955; Mar. 25, 1957; Apr. 1, 1957
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-.
Aug. 7, 1937; Aug. 14, 1937; Dec. 1, 1957
Pound, Arthur, 1884-1966.
In Topical File folder
Rockwell, Norman, 1894-1978
Sept. 3, 1948
Shore, Dinah, 1917-1994.
Feb. 4, 1956
Sigler, Kim, b. 1894
Nov. 17, 1948
Sloan, Alfred P. (Alfred Pritchard), 1875-1966.
Folders 84, 85
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
In Topical File folder
Thomas, Lowell, 1892-
Dec. 15, 1955; Apr. 3, 1957
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Feb. 4, 1937; Jan. 6, 1943; Sept. 27, 1943; May 4, 1949; May 5, 1949; May 12, 1949; Oct. 31, 1949; May 23, 1950; Mar. 14, 1952; Aug. 9, 1952; Aug. 15, 1952; Jan. 14, 1953; Dec. 24, 1957
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Apr. 29, 1953
Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Selective Index to Subjects
African Americans--Michigan
Letters January 26, 1937 and undated relating to the use of the word "negress" in the Flint Journal; also letter of John Gibson, June 24, 1938, relating to the treatment of Joe Louis in the newspapers
China--History--1949-1976
Letter from Gene (last name unknown) relating to post-war China, October 18, 1948
General Motors Corporation
Letters of January 31, 1939; also correspondence with Hugh Munro, May 11, 1955, May 17, 1955, and Sept. 2, 1955; also General Motors "sit-down strike" files
Jews--Michigan
Letter of Rabbi Elmer Berger, February 21, 1938, concerning newspaper coverage of a Nazi speaker in Flint.
Michigan. Civil Service Study Commission
Letters of James K. Pollock, Aug. 7, 1937, Aug. 14, 1937, and Dec. 1, 1957
Sit-down strikes--Michigan--Flint
Letter of Senator Arthur Vandenberg, February 9, 1937; also General Motors "sit-down strike" files
Related Material
The researcher should note that additional Michael Gorman papers have been given to the Alfred P. Sloan Museum in Flint, Michigan.